"life would go on as it had always gone on."
That is, badly.
Apart from the disputes over the windmill, there was the question of the defense of the farm.
It was fully realized that though the human beings had been defeated in the
Battle of the Cowshed, they might make another and more determined attempt to
recapture the farm and reinstate Mr.
Jones.
They had all the more reason for doing so because the news of their defeat had
spread across the countryside and made the animals on the neighboring farms
more restive than ever.
As usual, Snowball and Napoleon were in disagreement.
According to Napoleon, what the animals must do was to procure firearms and
train themselves in the use of them.
According to Snowball, they must send out more and more pigeons and stir up
rebellion among the animals on the other farms.
The one argued that if they could not defend themselves, they were bound to be conquered.
The other argued that if rebellions happened everywhere, they would have no
need to defend themselves.
The animals listened first to Napoleon, then to Snowball,
and could not make up their minds which was right.
Indeed, they always found themselves in agreement with the one who was speaking at the moment.
At last the day came when Snowball's plans were completed.
At the meeting on the following Sunday, the question of whether or not to begin
work on the windmill was to be put to the vote.
When the animals had assembled in the big barn, Snowball stood up and, though
occasionally interrupted by bleating from the sheep, set forth his reasons
for advocating the building of the windmill.
Then Napoleon stood up to reply.
He said very quietly that the windmill was nonsense and that he advised nobody
to vote for it and promptly sat down again.
He had spoken for barely 30 seconds and